Hoping to do a lot of work this week.
Some people are coming to help.
So pointing the walls...
We'll probably do that in a few days.
And in between,
we'll also do some digging work.
I think the excavator is being delivered.
End of the afternoon
or tomorrow afternoon. We’ll see
And already start
digging out the hillside.
And then dig trenches around, for drainage.
Because, as you can see, there's a bit of
water coming through the concrete.
It's not really leaking, like concrete
is waterproof,
but it's not completely impermeable.
It's like a porous material.
So if water sits against it,
the concrete gets wet
and that comes through the floor.
So it needs a barrier.
It's probably easier
to explain it in a drawing.
And then there's also the same thing
I have to do on the second cabin.
And I have to dig trenches to the battery
box for extra power to the workshop
and, split it up
because it's too much to do in one time.
It would be a big mess.
So just do the digging here.
Maybe the trenches to the battery box
But not all around the second cabin
A quick drawing
So water that comes down the hill here
kind of pulls up here, and it can’t go away
quick enough.
So it sits in the soil
and it sits against concrete.
So the concrete sucks it up, basically.
So I'll put a drainage pipe here
in the ground and dig it out all around.
And a drainage pipe
sits all around the cabin
so water can go through
the pipe down hill,
and probably the rain gutter pipe that will be on the back will also be connected to this.
So water can stream down to...
for the moment it'll come out of the hill
here.
But eventually
I'll connect everything together also with the system for the second cabin.
For the other side....
So from the top, it will look like this.
This is downhill.
These are the two cabins.
This is the workshop.
So the pipe sits in the ground around it.
So it will go around the corner
stream downhill from there
And here I will connect it to the system.
There will be another system here.
And there is already a pipe in the ground here
We have an ant problem.
A lot of ants coming through the wall.
And I saw dust at the shelf, and I thought it was things
eating up the beams.
I thought it was wood powder,
but it's actually mortar
there are little holes still in the pointing
of the wall and the ants coming through.
Somehow they're breaking up the wall. So.
I think they're behind the woodpile.
So I'm going to investigate.
Finn is here to help with pointing the walls
But, yeah, I think half a bag for sure.
You need in there
As soon as it disappears in here,
you can add your mortar
Yeah.
So the stiffness, you see it?
It doesn't.
So it's nice and thin, but it also stays....
It's perfect.
So for this it's important to keep it
Keep it liquid.
So if we fill it up
and we keep it stirring in the bucket
you just follow the stones
Sometimes it's a bit
hard already, but if you move it,
the same as in the bucket, it gets soft again
Here I didn’t do it well enough
See? this is a mistake.
But I think it was also because
I didn't make the stones wet enough. So.
And when they're not clean enough.
And dust is on it, it drops down
So yeah, that's how it works.
Tom has joined
Cheers, guys!
Cheers!
Thanks for having us.
Mostly welcome...
Most welcome! haha
That’s a different meaning
And then about 5 or 6 years ago,
well, I was in Germany at the time,
and I was like, okay, then I go home.
Now I'm going to right, make a right
good goal.
by getting good at basket making.
It's, you know, I wanted to be good at it.
And then Covid came.
So I was just kind of teaching myself
for  a while
Did you find good books?
there are good books
Yeah, a lot of books
written by English people, thankfully.
So, and then I got to go to other basket
makers, but the best basket makers
Really, in Ireland, if not the world
or in the English
speaking world, are in Galway.
He's an old guy
now, maybe in his late 70s, maybe.
Joel.
But he's in great
condition, he has really looked after himself.
And he documented it in the 70s.
Yeah, so he brought like an academic edge to it.
But then he himself
became a really good basket maker.
And now his son does it
So I was lucky, I only lived
about 45 minutes away from them.
So I spent a lot of time with them.
That's a great story, I love that
I got lucky
because now that was 5 or 6 years ago.
Now I look at the business
and I think my days are numbered
because in in my one area
alone, there's like six of us.
Oh wow
So it's really getting popular
I’ll gather up these stones tomorrow.
What's the plan now?
So, yeah,
levelling this out, bring it to the corner.
Do you edit videos every night?
No, at the end of the week.
End of the week, Saturday I edit
Beautiful morning.
got a lot of rain yesterday, but,
cleared up nicely.
Finn is here
He was helping also with pointing the walls
downstairs three years ago.
He liked it so much,
He came back
from Germany
and, also,
Tom, from Ireland.
He's a basket maker.
And, I think he's going to try
to make a basket
from Birch.
Or Willow, if we find it.
There is less willow here. But,
you know, curious.
But I think we'll
we'll get them from here.
If they were only cut a week
or two ago.
That's perfect material.
Okay.
But bendy definitely is fundamental.
With spring in it.
So do you see
the the other smaller ones
that I'm cutting off?
Okay.
If you just cut the side branches off
so that we were left with the main stem.
Like a baby.
the cut side down.
Yeah.
Next one right there.
no on the other side.
But this part down?  just this side, good.
Oh, wow.
Yeah. Brilliant.
I love that
And it’s all birch, right?
There's some Rowan in it too
But mostly birch.
And I've never worked with it before
So I'm giving myself forgiveness.
See what happens with the
with basket makers.
But I presume it's the same in everything.
Perfection, and on nothing
other than perfection will do.
And when we get to other people's baskets,
we tend to rip them apart, you know?
And I like if you're going to do something
new, you have to go easy on yourself.
Yeah, yeah.
And then it needs to cure in a way
or it just will slowly dry up
it will slowly dry.
It should shrink a bit
but I don't actually know
how much it's going to shrink,
because I've never worked with Birch.
Not much, right?
I mean,  the thickness of the branches will shrink,
the diameter, and then should loosen a bit.
But as far as I'm concerned,
that's a good basket.
It is, it’s beautiful
Yeah.
So maybe if you could get it,
I might move somewhere for the cutting
I'd say clean it. because
this is going to be cut off like that.
Yeah.
I built in the handles, do you like that?
I do like it
Wow. Thanks, man.
Yeah no, good!
Beautiful!
fucking love it man. Yeah.
make up for the one I left behind.
And this is perfect for me
because I just put it on my hip
Love it.
Decent size
quite heavy, for now
Let me get a shot of you
holding it.
the reason why I'm here,
Eric has joined
same as on the other side?
Yeah.
Otherwise you... like here we have a bit of a dip
but it's important that it goes gradually down
Do I need more sticks
or do you have enough?
should be plenty
little more.
Yeah. We're getting close here.
Okay, a little bit.
I'm good, I'm good, we're good.
Let's we drop it.
Drop it.
We're going to have to come up here.
Oh, yeah. Up there like.
let the lad run
So from here
now you're saying just have good aim.
Is it? okay
Yeah.
That's sound. Yeah,
yeah.
Not tip it, shovel.
Are you saying tip? no
There must be a way to dump it.
Perfect half moon, look at that
a slice of watermelon,
I'm coming over to you.
Can you clear that area?
Yeah.
I want to get the view, man.
I got my back to the mountains.
I feel like a fool.
I've seen the view, I’ll sit here
Those potatoes are amazing.
Never gets old.
It's just.
It's such a difference with the boiling potatoes, it’s so good
I think if
If you boil potatoes, you kind of wash them down.
Yeah.
You know, all of the good things go out
They’re also perfectly cooked.
Do we still have
those old potatoes from yesterday?
should be in the cabinet.
I think.
Left cabinet.
Yeah.
Amazing weather these last days.
It's all fresh green leaves.
It's every year.
It's such a treat.
We've been able to do a lot of work.
It's quite tricky working at the back of
the hill with the digger.
It's such a tiny little machine.
And on the steep slope,
if you do it right, you dig out platforms first.
But then still the short
arm reaching down, it's tricky.
And I want to keep the hill intact
for now.
Eventually there will be proper terracing and a wall to keep...
I mean, to finish the work off
nicely, but,
it's going to take so much time
to do that.
So that's for later.
The priorities now is to get the workshop
finished,
the building will be dry
with the drainage in place,
and then the focus is on the second cabin
and then the next phase would be
as a big work like landscaping,
building, retaining walls also.
And in front of the first cabin
I need to do that.
Something like the garden beds for example.
I would love to build it in stone,
but if I do that now, I'm going to lose
a few weeks bring material on site, build
everything nicely in stone
and it needs, time and dedication to do it properly. So.
Yeah, that's how it works.
First the buildings finished
and then landscaping as a bigger, long term project.
But yeah, we were able to do it
eventually was a lot more difficult
than the first cabin
where we also built in drainage, it was a bit more accessible.
The hill is very steep on that side.
And but, yeah, most of it is in there.
I need a few more loads of gravel.
Two more, I think,
and then we can close the burrito.
And then
I'm not sure what I’ll do around.
Maybe gravel,
maybe put some pavement around it.
So you can easily
just walk around the workshop.
So. Yeah,
it's a good week.
Beautiful weather.
Guys were great.
I mean, I'm
so lucky to have these people here
always coming to help
interesting people as well.
Tom was like, a basket maker.
He does this as a professional
And, and Eric was here from new Jersey,
although he lives in Italy, but,
yeah, great group of people.
The ants are also gone.
Like, I took the woodpile away.
And then few days after
they just disappeared,
I put some boxes there
that will,
also get rid of a bigger nest.
But, it seems like they're gone, so.
All good.
So next week, more gravel
finishing, pointing in the wall maybe
almost halfway.
But that is also a big job.
Always underestimating
But continue on that next week.